IP Address - uniquely identifies a device on a network. Made up of 32 bits, broken into 4 groups of 8 (bytes or octets). Each octet is seperated by a dot, and has value from 0-255.
Example: 192.168.0.1

Some of an IP address identifies the network, the rest identifies a device on the network. 192.168.0.1/24 means that the first three octets identify the network and there are 1-244 host (device) addresses available (0 and 255 are reserved). These are called the netowork and host segments.

There are multiple classes (ranges) of IP address. The class can be determined from the three left-most (most significant) bits of the first octet.


subnet mask = 255.255.254.0 = 11111111.11111111.11111110.00000000
IP address  = 10.12.151.94  = 00001010.00001100.10010111.‭01011110‬

	11111111.11111111.11111110.00000000 (subnet mask)
AND     00001010.00001100.10010111.‭01011110‬ (IP address)
=	00001010.00001100.10010110.00000000
=	10.12.150.0 (network address)

The first host address is 10.12.150.1, which is the default gateway.

The address 10.12.150.255 is the broadcast adress, which sends the data to every device on the network. Devices are responsible for seeing if they are the intended recipient.

Network addresses are used so that external devices can send data into a network without knowing host IP's - they just send it to the network on the broadcast address.